# Kirill A. Konovalov

mail: konovalov@wisc.edu mail2: kirillkirill0@gmail.com Department of Chemistry University of Wisconsin-Madison

I specialize in studying complex protein and nucleic acid dynamics through computer simulations. My aptitude lies with physical chemistry, particularly, biophysical models based on methods ranging from quantum mechanics to residue-level coarse-grained, with a focus on Markov state models and enhanced sampling. Overall, my work has contributed to our understanding of biophysics, specifically, transcription with RNA polymerase II and antibody design.

#### Academic Positions

2021-current Post-doctoral researcher, Department of Chemistry, University of Wisconsin-Madison (Advisor: Prof. Xuhui Huang)

#### Current projects:

- o A computational study of the allosteric effect of mutations in Protein Phosphatase 2A that underlie cancer and intellectual disability
- A computational study of the interplay between chaperone Hsp70 and the folding of client proteins

#### Education

2017-2021

Ph.D. in Chemistry, Department of Chemistry, Hong Kong University of Science and Technology, Hong Kong (Advisor: Prof. Xuhui Huang)

- o Thesis: "Mechanisms of Transcription: RNA Polymerase II Elongation Complex with DNA Modifications Studied with Molecular Dynamics Simulations"
- In silico study of RNA polymerase II transcription with DNA modifications, using molecular dynamics simulations and Markov state models

2011-2017

Specialist in Fundamental and Applied Chemistry, Lomonosov Moscow State University, Department of Chemistry, Russia, with honors, (Advisor: Prof. Andrey Golovin)

- Thesis: "A study of phosphonate-hydrolyzing antibodies"
- *In silico* design of phosphonate hydrolyzing abzymes, employing dynamics simulations, metadynamics, simulations and protein structure modeling

#### **Professional Skills**

- Primary skills: conducting and analyzing molecular dynamics simulations with atomistic and coarse-grained models, Markov state models, enhanced sampling methods (e.g., metadynamics, REST), *in silico* protein design (Rosetta), QM/MM simulations
- Coding: Python, R, Java, jQuery, Angular, C/C++

## **Primary Publications**

Google scholar

- 1. **Konovalov**, **K.A.**, Unarta, I.S., Cao, S., Goonetillekel, E.C., Huang, X.\*, "Markov state models to study the functional dynamics of proteins in the wake of machine learning", *J. Am. Chem. Soc. Au*, 1(9), 1330-1341, (2021)
- 2. **Konovalov**, **K. A.**, Wang, W., Wang, G., Goonetilleke, E. C., Gao, X., Wang, D., & Huang, X. A comprehensive mechanism for 5-carboxylcytosine-induced transcriptional pausing revealed by Markov state models. *Journal of Biological Chemistry*, 296, (2021)
- 3. **Konovalov**, **K.A.**, Pardo-Avila, F., Tse, C.K.M., Oh, J., Wang, D., Huang, X., 8-oxo-guanine DNA damage induces transcription errors by escaping two distinct fidelity control checkpoints of RNA polymerase II, *Journal of Biological Chemistry*, (2019)

## Fellowships and Awards

- 1. 2017-2021, Hong Kong Ph.D. fellowship scheme (Hong Kong)
- 2. Scientific debate competitions between teams:
  - o 2015 1st prize, Tournament of Three Sciences (Voronezh, Russia)
  - o 2015 2nd prize, Students tournament of Natural Sciences (Minsk, Belarus)
  - 2014 3rd prize, Biotournament (Puschino, Russia)

## **Teaching Experience**

2017-2019

Teaching assistant, HKUST, Hong Kong

- Laboratory for General Chemistry I (CHEM1050)
- Physical Chemistry Laboratory (CHEM2450)
- Molecular Characterization Laboratory (CHEM3555)
- o Mathematical Methods in Physical Chemistry (CHEM 2409)